hi all good evening hello all guys am I audible and visible hi Kabir thank you
nice let me share my screen
please let me know if you can see my screen share also
so we are going to end our classes on JavaScript next week isn't it next week
let me see how many classes are left yeah I think four classes are left on
JS part so one thing call out is that you know post JS there will be a
contest and also mock interviews case so I hope you guys are preparing for the
contest firstly contest like revise all the topics revise all the things that we
have discussed over the time okay if there is any challenge during any
of time whatever we have discussed I've been always available whoever ping me I
try to respond them personally anyway with any way of communication and even
in case you feel anything there's something left behind to discuss or
teach or you know topic that is being discussed please bring it up so that we
can you know discuss on that topics other than anything in curriculum okay
Kabir so are you talking about asynchronous JavaScript things we have
discussed on promises and okay so this thing related to promises async await
keep keep the oops part aside but other than those two classes call blind bind
apply and we have seen examples related to call bind apply and then we have
discussed asynchronous JS like those are concepts right in order to introduce
concepts we have discussed with those examples I've also shown you one of the
API read JSON builder where you can actually you know communicate with a
real-time API and how you do it so those concepts are actually not theoretical
but those concepts are really important like from interview perspective to know
or answer like if someone asks you what is asynchronous JS how does it execute
how does things handle what is your promise or promised at all settled race
conditions you should be knowing all of this stuff because in a way around when
you actually do good do and you know build a project you are going to come
across this topics very frequently very very frequently if you remember one of
the project we build a very small project called weather app in that you
are actually making an API call to weather API which was giving you a data
depending upon users input right so you should be knowing it how we are
actually handled handled it like if you go back into the code now we will be
able to relate more why async await was added and what is actually happening
behind the scenes right so it's more of with practice it will come we'll see
usage of them more and more but you know since those were topics introduction
that's how it can be thought that's one that's my idea but for more practical
use cases right when you actually consume more amount of APIs when you
actually build projects then you will be seeing that part of asynchronous
okay so if there are any other concerns or any other doubts right related to
anything topics that we have discussed on the day one of our classes for this
full stack if you have anything please raise it raise them like we'll have a
discussion on that part okay let me start stop watch so majority of things
could be like if you see like all the things that you see in the network tab
right whatever calls are being made in the network all these things are ready
to promise itself like how do you consume even the style sheets there
might be a API call which is actually putting the data that will be an also
need like you know promise rough-handed you go to any built-in application you
will see n number of API calls are being done let's say if I reload this page so
let's say if you see these two calls are done how would you consume their data so
in order to understand all of them you have to know what's a behind the scenes
things are happening so we'll come to them each one by one step when you
actually how you build an API or how do you consume more amount of APIs are
doing with a post put update calls all of them you'll see great amount of
examples post react but currently we are introducing a good topics at our length
right if I overburden you guys with more more amount of more things then it would
be really difficult to get the understanding about the topics that we
are discussing so anyone else having any other doubts guys anyone else having
any other doubts does anyone else feels same as Kabir that the topics that we
have recently discussed are more like you know or theoretical but connecting
them with the real-time will take more time for you guys
I see one thumbs up okay let's bring in chat guys like whatsapp but just let me
know whether are you able to follow up with whole asynchronous JS have you got
the understanding about asynchronous JS right
okay yeah so that things will come guys like with practice like as some bit
says you if you see building projects is an actual use case where you will be
seeing it as we build few more projects you'll be seeing them but few things
comes from our point of view is that actually teaching you the basics of it
then building things up on that one right so but any any other doubts like
if you have any other concerns from the topics we have discussed in case if you
didn't understand any of the use case do let me know okay because asynchronous
JS is one of the interviewers kind of favorite topic when they want to really
understand things right how you would you make a series calls now when I say
that we are all we have discussed in terms of like calls right making series
consuming data from third source party like it can be file or simple array or
object or any data source so these are the most common use cases where you're
going to deal with them at real time how would you consume all of them and how
would you use use easy use case like this will come with more amount of
experience like when to make what sort of calls and all those things still I
see okay but any other things guys if you want to flag if you have any
challenges but I want to talk about one thing is that again our disclaimer we
have four classes left in order to complete HTML CSS and JS part this will
cover all core fundamentals and basics of your web development once these are
done we'll be moving with the react react JS to be specific make sure that
you are pretty much clear with each of topic so that we leverage this in a
better way so that we can understand this thing in a better way I hope this
point is clear guys so that if you are clear with this each of one you will be
able to understand this one in a better way if you are lacking somewhere then it
would be a tricky for you also like why even if I explain multiple times there
might be a few things that you should be knowing basics of them and these are the
basics that we have covered hope you revise everything and there will be a
context coming after this for class so be prepared with them so that you you
know test your knowledge right so be prepared with that part and try to
attempt it okay will it be theoretical I'm not exactly sure something let's
let's not keep it that way let's go and try it out okay it will be 50-50 you can
say okay there might be some questions asked there might be things on a
synchronous chairs okay but as I've seen that most of the people who were
actually attending classes and you know trying to attend the mock sorry contest
they are doing better and they're also raising flags on questions like how
there can be multiple answers or the P1 answer is wrong I appreciate your
efforts and going into you know understanding each of them one by one
but if there is someone who haven't taken earlier marks right I would request
everyone of you go and take you know in the practice mode open the can we pick
it up once we get started with that topic actually because that would be
better way to explain things on that okay great just a second guys I just
want to see how we are doing in terms of batch
anyways so this can we get started with today's content great so let's not wait
anymore and we'll get started with this class I think good enough people are
there that's 12 minutes up now so today's class and the class is mostly
based on some topic called polyphils okay but now I have raised this word
earlier also but do you know what this polyfill is what why we call it as a
something called as a polyfill does anyone know this keyword I see one
thumbs up can you two people can you guys type it down personally to me what
you understand by a polyfill guys Muneshwar Opendra what's your understanding
related to it what is an polyfill okay nice Muneshwar are you typing it down
okay great so there are two definitions that I got it both are actually trying
to explain what polyfill is but let's see let's understand going back to
JavaScript right where does this HTML JS and CSS are actually passed into and
where this are working on which is the machine is actually executing them
guys I think everyone knows this answer just want to know like where do you
where you use actually this HTML CSS and where this is actually executed or
past like where do you open a website what is a tool you use to open a
website browser right now all these things are done in a browser now if you
remember browser is providing us some API's right like API's when I say
inside a window you will see that there is something like document there is
something like location there are storages most of the things are being
provided by a browser right guys do you agree that browser is actually providing
us this list of API's to in order to build or develop now even if I type down
like array at heart if you see remember in our inspect console tab I used to
type it down array.prototype right all of those things I used to type it down
and this array is also defined where if I write down directly in a browser I'm
able to access array right I'm able to write down console directly logics how
this is able to work
this is because whenever you install browser right all JS code is already
present in that array array related information is there object related
information is there function function related information is there do you guys
agree with that part guys that everything is present in the browser
be pre-packed like if you want to see let's say this is an browser where we
haven't written any code but if I go into console like I can type down array
see I'm having this number of arrays I can type down object if you see I'm
getting this amount of things this all things are actually coming along with
the browser itself now who is actually building the browser am I are we
responsible or any companies are responsible or is there any common body
or everyone have their own set of specifications who is actually owning
or managing the browsers guys who is actually managing the browsers
companies like let's say who is who is the owner of Chrome Google everyone
knows that then if I write Bing who is the owner of Bing Microsoft and then
Safari
Apple so even there is one more thing Firefox just Mozilla corporation now are
the developers of this four companies sitting together and building this apps
or their each individual team is actually building as per their own
requirement each everyone is building as per their own use case right whatever
they want to add that's where that's where this different browsers are like
we might prefer Chrome better than any other or Bing is preferred better than
Firefox Safari now the developers specifically prefer Chrome there's a
reason for that because we were able to debug in a better way we are able to see
the code write down the things isn't it that's where Chrome is actually better
application now even if you go these are the latest browsers but do you remember
something like Internet Explorer Netscape old browsers these are old
browsers now let's say this is actually managed by Microsoft itself isn't it
now Microsoft in between left this project and they started this one right
Bing from scratch again to compete with the world the left Internet Explorer
they stopped releasing new versions and this they built this one but if you see
what happened our HTML CSS JS code all is passed into this set of machines and
this set of machines are not same each company is building own machine and we
don't know where things will be working right now so what poly fields are let's
say there are some latest versions let's say there are some functions let's say
there is some like let's say you say that some methods newly introduced
mothers let's say promised at all okay we need to see whether this particular
method is actually supported in all of them we are not sure right we don't know
whether all these things are supporting that one we know that this promised at
all is coming from browser we have checked in the chrome but our website is
not specifically supposed to run in chrome is it supposed to run in all the
applications right wherever user opens do you guys agree with that point we
have to build application cross-functional sent it now there is a
one website do you guys know this can I use this actually websites gives you
information about actually which feature is available in which browser like it
shows a browser compatibility let's say if I tried on promised at all and enter
it what it gives me it gives me the different browsers like chrome it's
Safari Firefox Opera right now they'll give you actually let's say promised at
all JavaScript built-in or promised our
prototype but finally all these methods where they are available if you see in
the Internet Explorer is not supported anymore okay this this actually website
gives you information about like which is actually supporting right now in
case in case let's say if you see opera mini right opera mini that doesn't have
any information here we don't know if they are supporting it like promised at
all sector or UC browser do you remember UC browser Chinese browser which used to
come in mobile right by the browser so there are many things there are
different machines built by different teams so we don't know whether it is
actually supported if you see our promised at all sector is actually
supported for the ninety five percent and promised at all is supported ninety
six percent but there are some use cases which are not actually supported now but
how do you deal with them like what if let's say if you see a banks right banks
even in most of the let's five years back banks used to prefer I browser do
you know this they used to prefer only Internet Explorer mostly five years back
they actually used to write now a person like a web developer like us was
actually building for a crow and this people Microsoft people are not you know
building this one but whatever we are supporting chrome we are supposed to
support in this IE then what we used to do right if there is a some API or some
method like let's say this is a promised at all is available in chrome not
available in IE then we used to write a custom function like a promise start my
all which used to actually take care of replicating the behavior what actually
doing so that we ourselves are building this common API's and so that it is
supported in cross browsers and this custom function whatever you have
written which is replicating actual behavior in order to support all the
application this is called a polyfill polyfills for the non supportive
browsers or non you know which doesn't have that feature is this point here
is what is polyfill now so this is actually five years before five years
this was actually one of the interviews focused questions because they used to
ask them specifically because web once you develop in one browser it should be
supporting in other browsers so how would you make it compatible so if you
are this is a production bug right so no one wants like one working in one web
not working in other web so you they they used to specifically see whether a
developer is able to write the code but today's world mostly all the browsers
are well maintained and they're doing it well the teams are doing well to keep it
up with you keep it up with in sync with ECMA script but what happened is like
because this was asked in earlier interviews they're still asking right
writing up polyfills write a polyfill for let's say some for some dash any
function whichever you have it in JavaScript they asked you to write your
own library method is this clear guys what polyfill is and why we have to
learn it and why the interviewers used to ask and okay so now we have two
classes on polyfills first okay these are interview specific so one in class
we will discuss about discuss about HOF in other class we'll discuss about call
wind up like okay we'll discuss these two topics okay in today's class we'll
cover HOF where if you see an array with three had three functions map filter
reduce and for each okay if time permits I'll pick up flat also this five
functions this five functions without using these functions will write our own
okay we'll try to implement on our own guys I'll come to that some bit I'll
come to that we'll talk about that okay but we have to we have other than flat
we have discussed each of this function isn't it I hope all of you know the
meaning of it so that we'll get started with this implementation okay let's say
I go back into our code now if even if you go and see this right filter let's
say if I search it let's say in global if you see only 17 percent they
supported all other people are not supporting it like most people are you
see in Chrome they are not supporting it particularly you can verify like where
it is supported why it is not supported okay you can use this website well pin
this one I mean back in my days when I used to code for Deutsche Bank I used to
use this website because they used to use IE Internet Explorer which was like
really difficult for me to write any logics and cross browser testing we had
to do we had to do many things okay and other than this thing guys I have added
the screenshots which you asked for me like related to this okay guys I hope
you are able to understand when I when I have written this way I try to replicate
it what we have written in notes like so that you can figure out the output and
also I added related to slice and splice because this is also asked in
interview like what's the difference between array dot slice or array dot
splice okay hope you go through this one push this code already okay thank you
guys so let's start with our last coding okay first and foremost polyfill
that we are going to pick is about for each let's say for the start chase now
yeah class number 27 right some so guess how do you define for each what do you
think for each is firstly just want to know what's your understanding on for
each let's say I have array of 1 2 3 4 5 6 let's say this number numbers are
there now what for it used to help me out every item in an array it is an
iterator can I say it is an iterator right let's say if I do array dot for
each first it used to take a callback function isn't it it takes a callback
function inside this callback function it used to provide support like what all
it used to provide support it used to give each element to us also it is to
provide index right if you remember callback function value current element
value and index and the array itself like if you need even array you will be
able to access it let me show you once an outputting this thing how this thing
looks let's say index and array all of them
clear node
okay if you see it here what just happened it prints first number like
element one then it is you give me index and then it is giving me an array right
and depending on whatever operation whatever operation I have to do let's
say if I'm trying to multiply each element let's say I try to say that
return element into twice okay let's say I'm doing this logic now tell me one
thing does this for each returns anything or does it for each returns
anything or it's just like an iterator it's like a for loop do I get anything
in return by directly or it manipulates existing array what do you think like
if I do console dot log array what it should be if whether this it will be
multiplied all the things will be multiplied like two four six eight what
could be the output here firstly when I print array itself like it should be
this order or it should be this order it manipulates existing array okay how
many if you think that it if you think that it is manipulating existing array
give me thumbs up if you think that it doesn't manipulate existing array give
me thumbs down okay three people say that it manipulates okay let's see this
what is actually happening if I try to print it now okay clear it if I try to
do this do you see it here that it doesn't manipulate existing array
firstly guys whoever give me four thumbs up it is not actually touching the
existing array but it you know multiplies each index and whatever you
need it right you have to store in a new array value okay if you see let's say
if now whether this will be actually returning here you see here I'm trying
to store in something in array one whether this will be having anything
value now what could be the output of area one case firstly I'll come to that
I'll come to that but do you think that what will do think here output should be
two four six or here we have figured out that it is one two three itself let's
it is two four six if you see I'm receiving an undefined check now if I
want to manipulate let's say if I want to manipulate existing array firstly you
know remember one thing for each doesn't return new array okay it doesn't return
new array if I want to if I want to manipulate existing array what I can do
it here is that I can select array dot index equal to this one is this clear
if I want to manipulate existing array I have an index I have the current element
I have an array I can I can take that existing array I can point to each of
index and update it now let's see this start if it is updating let's say this
is I'll comment this one let's keep it let's keep it so that you remember that
it doesn't return anything now do you see this it got updated we are getting
four two four six now in array also I hope this point is clear related to
footage it is just like an iterator it doesn't any do anything it is like if
you want to iterate over the each element it iterates it doesn't do
anything else I hope you got it it's just like first loop nothing each
nothing much now if you want to replicate let's say if someone asked you
in the interview can you can you build this can you build and give me a poly
fill for this one for the for each function how would you approach it what
would be your idea let's say now what how I want to execute this let's say for
I'll say like my footage and I want to do this thing let's say copy everything
here okay guys now whenever I try to do again I know if I'm again outputting it
it should be giving me an actual output of four eight to well since once we have
multiplied it already here we will be replicating again if I try to do a
console lock below it should be updating it now it's some bits it's create a
function I takes three parameters okay any anyone else case anyone else having
ideas like firstly it is available on my array array dot my footage how would I
how should it be how we can make sure that it is it should be available on
array dot how should we make make sure that it is available for all the arrays
because we are building up array I'm in a utility method on an array type and
it should be supporting each and everything so one thing we can do is
that let's say I built I build on the top what I'll say that array dot
prototype now how many of you understand this word prototype is there anyone with
this who don't understand my prototype okay I hope everyone understands what's
prototype and why I am writing it this way now let's say here I'm having a
function okay good now this is the function now on this array now every
array whichever is built actually you know leveraging on every array my for
each will be available now once I do this but how this should work they
should try to replicate the same behavior firstly let's think of this
thing what my for each is taking what is this what it is taking firstly what is
for each is taking as a parameter
approach step by step guys what it is taking a function right and what we can
call that function as callback function can we say that it's a callback function
right let's say that it takes a callback function in it right can I say this
guys no if I if I try to do this let's say if I try to do here now just one
question guys if you understand this keyword properly just tell me what this
will point out inside here what will be this pointing to inside inside this
function it should point out to a function or it should point out to an
array because we are doing everything is an object which everything is an object
in JS we have understood behind the scenes right so array should be this
should be pointing to ARR right because we are calling array dot my for each so
this keyword will be actually pointing to array which is this one okay once I
have this now what should be my next step guys this is pretty much simple if
you are able to think it what does for each is doing
once have an access to array what what should I do pick up each element now in
order to pick up each element what should I do it use for loop right let's
say I have to write a for loop let index I should write the in a for loop on this
array right on this array which is actually I'm receiving this dot length
guys are you able to understand this like why I'm writing this for loop now
inside this for loop for each element for each element am I calling this call
back function for each element in this array one by one I'm calling this call
back right same thing I'm doing it right for each of this element I'm actually
making a calling a call back let's say we we call a call back now while
executing call back what all things it is expecting the call inside the call
back it's expecting three things isn't it the current element how can I get an
access of current middleman can I say this dot index and I can pass on index
and then I can pass on this right yes I did you understood this one this is an
actually prototype of for each let's say execute this one let's execute this one
whether this is working or not now do you see this first a general for each
function which was returning me once I executed this part on this array it was
returning multiplied by two four six eight then we built our custom logic my
for each and we implemented proto fill a polyfill for that one and we executed
then we got output of four eight well I hope this polyfill is clear to you if
there is anyone who don't understand this do let me know I'll wait for two
three minutes here okay if there is anyone I'll wait for two three minutes
so that you are able to get all the concepts that how we are actually
creating a function on a library how we are replicating them step by step okay
is use case of for each is clear again and how does for each works and how can
you build a proto polyfill for each for the furry if someone asked you in the
interview would it be able to demonstrate this one taking an example
and building this again replicating this one yeah I would do that okay so first
thing remember one thing that for each actually doesn't return you anything
okay it just like an eye-treater it just I treat over the elements it doesn't do
anything else okay and it takes a callback function inside it and inside
the callback function it receives three parameters one is the current element or
the current index item you can say then you have the index of each item then the
whole array itself will be available as a third parameter using this you can do
anything that you want to do in a function body what I've just read is it
I'm updating the existing array information I wanted to replicate this
structure building my own custom polyfill such as such that I call it
like array dot my for each now I'm supposed to make this my for it should
be firstly available on all array data types so what did I do is that first I
created I've written this logic that array dot prototype prototype dot my
forage because it should be available in all array types of data types once this
is available I was trying to see this behavior firstly okay then I went step
by step I've seen that hey I have this up this keyword here and this is
actually pointing to an object now that object can be an array since everything
is an object in JS I'll be having an access to the array once I have an
access to array inside this I ran a loop over this which is an array itself and
call this callback function with these three parameters whichever this call
the pack is expecting okay is this clear guys
shadow let's move to new thing called map dot JS let's again I have this array
itself now what does map do is I just want to know if you remember what does
map do what's our difference between map and forage does anyone remember it what
map does it returns a new array right anything else case
okay let's say let's say that I write array dot map again does it take a
callback function guys some bit map that's something that you are
understanding keys and values it's a different thing but I'm talking about
higher-order function map here pointing to some bit wasn't not you trip some
bit party so that you understand that on array we have three higher functions map
filter and radius which are commonly used and extra one is for each okay I'm
talking about them so hope you are hope you got this point okay so as people are
suggested okay returns a new array and also again each element right it's an
iterator and it returns something whatever you do it operation now let's
say if I have three things again an element again if you see index again I'll
have whole array here available right once I have this now let's say I can
return element restrict twice now again again once one question does it still
changes or manipulates this array if I do a console log let's say if I do
console log of array what should be the expected output guys here does it affect
the existing array got it some bit like let's say I store it and again array one
but what could be the output of ARR what should be the output for this one what
should be output for this one so Ashish says that it will manipulate the
existing array also so do you guys agree that it should be two four six and here
also you are saying that it should be two four six is it so what should be an
output for this one guys firstly this is really basic concept I hope everyone
remembers how that what is the difference between for each and map any
random day anyone can ask you if you're a front-end developer anyone can ask you
this thing like even a block person right let's say there's too much blocking
happening on roads or streets in Bangalore or Hyderabad one can put up a
mic and ask you if you're a front-end developer say difference between map and
for each you should be able to say that it's really basic so firstly how many
of you think that the output should be one two three right so let's let's see
this one firstly I'll
node map dot JS if you can see this that it doesn't manipulate existing array
still not not even for each not even map touches your existing data I mean
data set your existing data structure is not changed in both use cases is that
point clear first point that in both use cases it doesn't change output of of the
same data set only a thing a main difference between map and for each is
that map returns you a new array like if you see I was able to store here in
array one and I was able to output it whereas in for each I was getting an
undefined when I was trying to output the array one so for each doesn't return
anything map returns or something man's map returns as a new array is this point
clear guys would you be able to answer difference between for each and map from
now on it's really important because if those are higher order commonly
reusable functions you will be using day in day out because the only two type of
data structure that you play around mostly in front-end is array and objects
so you should be knowing a good amount of like understanding on them okay now
let me show you our difference between for each and map this is not the right
article maybe images okay the return value is I hope you are able to see this
image
nice is this clear can you guys read it once from your point of view both the
use cases it doesn't modify original array for each returns as undefined
whereas map returns is like a new array let's say it says that new array is not
greater at the end of the method call which is exactly pointing out to the
second point itself here newer again okay this I mean I don't understand why
they say that new array maybe they are talking about in different context but I
hope this first two points are clear to you but what what is actually happening
right now let's go back to this no can anyone help me out or volunteer me to
build up route or polyfill for a map it's a completely same as her forage but
some small change just want to know if can anyone help me out or just I'll give
you five minutes guys just think of it like how would you build this one say
what I want to do what I want to do is start let's say I try to copy and paste
here but I'll say this is array 2 it's array 2 but I'll use my map yeah can
anyone write it down guys can anyone write it down and send me send the code
to me like for my map I'll wait for two three minutes they agree with your
points Ramya in some bit but can you would write it down because if I write
it down it's just like I can copy and paste off for each and I can change
something I'll also give you if you want to see this use case I can also give you
this thing now what would be the only changing thing here
guys is anyone trying it or everyone waits waiting for me to do it no
reactions do you want me to do it okay let's let's okay trying it trying great
guys keep going I'll wait for the for the two minutes
well what I'll do is that I'll just copy this one I'll keep it here on the
top now instead of for my each I'll do my map I have to change two things
inside it I just want to know what would you change it
yes can I move ahead okay some bad ass ish
okay somewhere the sing one minute okay
meanwhile others also can think like what we have to change it because it's
pretty simple and straightforward there's only one difference have we have
highlighted is that map returns you something whereas for this doesn't
return anything great on Ashish right somewhere agree so as ass is suggested
that we need to create firstly new array with some memory one thing I said is
that in JavaScript you doesn't really need to specify the size of an array you
can directly initialize an array with an empty okay you don't really need to say
that this start length that works but not needed okay if you are using
constructor function of new array like it should be this way new array only
when you do this then it can you know it will say it will ask you the length
like then you can pass on this start length this would be the syntax in case
if you want to create a new array with the certain length is this point here
guys like how would you actually create an array with a certain length I hope
everyone remembers that there's something like constructor function we
have discussed and every thing should be there so let's say not complicating it
this should be also working it now and this is something let's say we are
returning it response and each of the value each of the value I have to be
adding into this one right again I can do this thing or else I can do this
thing
anything works face both the things should work okay now how many of you are
able to understand this a small chain is that we are trying to create a new array
and pushing every element line by line because if you see whatever this callback
function is executing multiplying each index we are adding back into a new
array which is array one in a way right this array whatever this callback
function is actually executing it and whatever this function is returning it
like you can say element into two that we are pushing back into a response
let's say this is working fine now do you see this guys that my array 2 is
actually returning 2 4 6 8 10 I hope this logic is pretty much clear simple
basic and there is if you see here in the differences they talked about one
more thing guys this last point hoping if you are able to understand this last
point for each method is not chainable map is chainable what do you think this
is why do say that chainable not chainable anyone I see one thumbs down
two now since can I say this in one line that farage doesn't return anything to
make it a chain map returns you something so that you can add multiple
operations like you can you can filter things right do you guys agree that if
you want to do it let's say once you do this you will be able to filter it let's
say filter again say element return let's say element modulus of 2 now what
they should do actually what they should do what should be the output of here
what should my output be here guys this was my output earlier let's say
everything is even so let's make it odd or else let's let's do some condition
let's build since they are multiplying by 2 let's make it multiplying by 3 now
just we know that right we I think I hope we got the understanding what this
will actually do why changing is possible on my app not on farage okay
let's say I do this now if you see I'm able to get all the even numbers when
I'm trying to output of arrow to just like I'm trying to fetch like I can
filter it this is what a chaining means I hope this point is clear what what was
that table talking about like third point with the basic differences anyone
will be able you will be able to recall it right the difference between map and
forage and once they ask you difference between an app and forage would you be
able to build their poly fields to the fast great now now we'll move to the
filter function actually it's again pretty much similar guys again like if
I pick it up you have to help me out how would you do this let's say I have this
array and if I do this filter what I can do is that let's say again if you see
this this the callback function whatever callback function is there it again
receives three things value in index an array now this is a predicate predicate
something like based on condition something it does okay now let's say I
have element index again the whole array now what we'll do is that only if
element modulus of 2 is triple equal to 2 which I'll say instead of this adding
condition we can directly return it okay now one more question does filter again
does filter again change your existing array does it affect ARR would it
manipulate it or it will return something it would return an array isn't
it okay let's say I store it here and ARR 1 and I try to do console.log ARR 1
and again console.log ARR okay now let's recheck this output clearing it node
filter.js now I hope this point is clear how that filter is working it is returns
or something and this is also still like you can add any number of chainings that
you want okay yeah somebody is already thinking like how we can build polyfill
but I hope this function filter works how it works we know that right and you
guys give me one thumbs up if you know how does filter works it doesn't
manipulate existing array and it returns as based on some condition it is trying
to predicate something like possibility now again I am building something let's
say array 2 and let's say instead of filter I'll say my filter and if I try
to output again console.log array 2 it should be array 1 should be actually
value should be equal to array 2 okay now if I have to build it on my filter
filter on my array one of the common thing we have to do is like an array
dot prototype dot filter once I do this I'll have a callback function on this
callback function I have to do some condition one thing is common is that it
is still taking callback so let's add a callback cool again cross checking what
this is pointing to here the still is pointing to ARR isn't it right object
nice now how would you build a filter here I think Sambit has already done the
condition guys do you understand that what Sambit written in the chat able to
follow up so I'll try to write down the logic let's see firstly again
I treating through the loop I treating through all the items of an array then I
have to check only if if callback of now callbacks take three things here again
this start I and then I then this let's say instead of I I can make it again for
better you know muscle memory takes me to I we are used to DSA people usually
write IEJ those are things we remember right now only once this is only if this
condition is true we add it to the response right again response start
push I should off index I should be doing this start index and I should be
returning this guys is this logic clear to you let's say I say this mime filter
not overriding existing library right good now let's say if I execute this one
again okay if you see we are still getting both the same outputs for the
array 1 and array 2 so both are working as as expected so I hope this this thing
is clear but I didn't wait for this one because this is pretty straightforward
just like based on only condition if it is true whatever callback is executing
only if that condition is true only then we'll push it or else will exit will not
do anything if it is returning false right and this is the reason why I
explained about like whether truthy or falsy condition like how does it works
like in if condition when there is a particularly there is nothing like
return type if there is even value how that can be if we go inside the if loop
okay but I hope my filter for each and map is clear guys these three functions
you hope you will be able to write polyfill without some revision on it okay
then there is one thing which is you know reduce.js now how many of you
remember reduce guys I'll open an example that we discussed interesting
example I don't remember where it is
guys do you remember how does reduce works
it takes okay let's say I'll come to that I've actually shown you an example
of prefix sum right if you remember prefix sum calculating a prefix sum using
the reduce right I'll come to that I'll show that example again but let me
introduce again a reduce once for you all okay let's say again I have an array
again one two three let's I have this numbers reduce is actually a returns as
a value let's say it returns as a value not an array but it does such a way
firstly you know it's a it takes a callback function and it takes a two
parameters what will be the default value and what will be the let's say
initial value if I put it as zero why I'm putting it to zero is because I'm
trying to replicate some of elements let's say some of elements now when
there is no cancellation is done by default the value is zero it takes three
parameters one is accumulator then current value let's say if I write down
exactly the way it is showing previous value and it returns again an array okay
it is doing three things for us clear firstly also let's say if we what if we
receive index here the index have they they haven't exposed index in reducer is
it it should be there okay let's say good now what I can do if I want to use
this simply I have to do is like previous number plus equal to current
value this will do my calculations now how many of you recall this example how
many of you are able to understand this reduce how does it work if there is
anyone who doesn't understand reduce case give me thumbs down if there is
someone who don't understand reduce it is reducing all the numbers into a one
particular number where we are doing some of the all the numbers here
starting with zero as a previous value previous value is actually pointing
starting with zero then it keeps on adding with the current number the
current number will be one then two then three then it will keep on adding all
the numbers let's see this console dot log result clear mode reduce dot js just
a second did I make as I didn't return it sorry it should return the number
right right yes if you see it here we got the whole sum of the all the elements
I hope this example everyone remembers it so I'll go back to class that we
have discussed class number 10 where we try to calculate prefix sum and we
remember that for the prefix sum right we always used to return now everyone
remember this prefix sum right the sum of the previous all the elements with
the current element till that point now if you see this I have tried to
initialize the existing array which will be resulting this is a prefix sum array
in this callback function I mean two things an accumulator accumulator is a
previous value till now what is the accumulated data accumulated number and
the current value so what I say is that if there is if the item is itself first
number if the index is 0 then directly add it push it to this array the current
number because for the index one prefix sum of index one will be equal to the
same number isn't it sorry index 0 isn't it let's say if you have an array of 1 2
3 prefix sum would be 1 3 6 isn't it for the first index it should be this
condition right same thing whatever it is there push it into this one then if
the length is greater than it then I'm getting the previous sum whatever my
previous sum is there plus current value same use case I hope this example
everyone recalls it remembers it again rechecking with you if there is anyone
who don't understand reduce if there is anyone do let me know or else we are
moving ahead with implementing the polyfill for this one okay take it as
know that there are no doubts on reduce I hope everyone understands it but now
let's let's think of this one guys how would you implement this one what would
it take to build a polyfill for reduce let's say I call it the same logic I'll
copy this part instead of result I'll say result one and I'll say my reduce okay
and here on the top I'll basic syntax I'll write down prototype dot my reduce
on this let's say I have a function and this is what I'm doing same concept
isn't it Ashish it's it's still same isn't it it's what firstly let's go
step by step is it taking a callback function inside reduce firstly let's
decide what should go inside this parameters here first is it taking
callback function right let's say there's a callback function right it is
taking an initial value it is taking two parameters isn't it this reduce function
is saying two parameters callback function till here then no don't go
inside the callback function somewhere first seen on terms of reduce level
itself so if I cut down this one I write down const so CP is it taking two things
inside my reduce
guys right so we have to say that also along with the callback function I'll
have something like initial value this is clear guys that it should have
something like initial value first now what if what if there is no initial
value provided what should you do if there is no initial value provided let's
say I try to let's I try to comment this part let's say that we remove this zero
initial value and I try to print this again what it is taking by default it
is taking as zero okay now even if I let's say if I try to multiply it it is
still does it take like one here if it takes zero if it takes zero then it
multiplication should be zero of everything isn't it you get this point
guys okay so now what I'll do is that I'll give a break of six seven minutes I
want everyone to explore like how should you handle the initial value if you see
for one use case it took it as zero for any use case it took it as one now how
would you define like what should the exact value what in case if there is no
initial value provided if it is an undefined how would you handle it okay do
you need break guys or should we continue I think that people are not
responding today too much guys I hope everyone is able to follow up it's not
boring yeah condition for initial value figure out that thing guys that if you
see I've shown you two use cases I have removed initial value for this
existing function where I'm trying to find some of values in that condition it
considered initial value zero but when I try to multiply it multiplying all the
numbers then it considered as a one is that point here explore that summit I
will discuss with after the break for the five minutes let's take the break
for five minutes and come back okay
I have started break let's meet in five minutes
you
guys is everyone back
do you guys think what should be the how would you handle if initial value is not
provided
okay if not can we can we do it and I'll explain back let's say firstly
whether whether firstly what we are resulting is like it's a constant value
right we are resulting in a one constraint value let's say that I have
a response and it is pointing to let's say initial value itself okay because we
are supposed to return response okay in between we know that we have this
operator which is actually giving me the array itself till here no doubts right
till here no doubts I hope
guys this point is clear right this is pretty much basic now what I'll do here
for response I'll check first if response exists what I'm trying to check
whether response exists what in general what I'm practicing whether initial
value is provided if not provided this will become undefined isn't it so I hope
you got this condition so if value is undefined I'll say that pick it up
initial value initial value of array or else if value is provided in the right
way then you go on to do the operations what operations you will do again in the
callback if you see I have something that previous number where I'll store
it in a response then I have the current number which is this dot I then I'll
have I then I'll have this initial value points to this dot 0 if undefined right
right something so this is what this is how you can handle it like if undefined
will directly go for pointing out to first key then for the all other
iterations it will you know take from that level if not if it is provided it
keep on taking that initial values okay I hope that point is clear guys so let's
execute this one whether this is working as expected say uncomment this logic I
put back this call back inside here I remove the CB okay let's execute this
one again no okay I made a constant variable let me make it as lit right
now I got something is like I've seen for plus let's say first first we'll
verify for the plus both are 5555 and if I check for the multiplication for the
both the things with provided value as one first we will check with provided
value both things are one if I don't give any value even let's verify this
again both are still resulting in same things so I hope this polyfill is also
clear guys like how this thing works for reduce function to can I receive one
final check from you guys like all of you can you give me a wooden please I
just if all these functions are because these are the three functions that you
would be asked map reduce filter where people try to grill on they check on
your kind understanding first you do understand this once you they you say
that you understand this they might ask you to write a polyfill on that okay if
this thing is clear I'll talk about one final method which we haven't talked
about it yet flat dot JS have you anytime heard about flat added or flat
okay I see no one notice
now what do you see here this yeah flatten you might have seen like flatten
the binary tree flatten the linked list these questions you guys came across
this one anytime what do you generally do in flatten whenever you have a tree
you would try to arrange them in one an array right one array like if you have a
iron inside array if you see this is a two level nested level you try to make
it one level nested is this clear what actually array dot flat does it's the
same functionality let's say array dot if I take pick it up flat inside flat it
takes depth what does it exactly mean by depth is that how many levels of
recursion calls it should do that if I am having this is level of one level
this is a two level if I write down level one okay and try to store here
firstly let's see what happens if I store it if I make it level one and try
to print it no flat dot JS if you see what just happened is it flattened all
to the level one right it went into the depth of initial array then it went to
level one let's say if I have it this way okay this is this is 0th level first
level since second level now let's see what happens if I try to print it again
do you see that 2 and 3 is still in array if I increase the level further if I
increase the level further now it will completely flat it up okay generally the
parameter inside this one is taking like how many times it should you know
recursively check the condition nested condition how many times it should
iterate through that I hope that point is clear like what depth is actually
meant we what are the what is the value I'm actually why I am passing this one
two or not passing anything if you don't pass anything what happens just let's
see if you don't pass anything what is a default value also it doesn't do
anything the depth level is zero it returns whatever array it is so did you
understand what is flat what do you mean by flat flattening an array right
this is an algorithm that you have already practiced for the different data
structure in your DSA can you guys think like how would you do it let's say this
is like a simple data structure DSA problem right flatten the array let's
say that I write a function flat and ARR I give an array you just go and do
this logic part this can be asked in any interview like how can you make an array
flat any any ideas guys how would you approach this one okay so these are what
is actually happening if you see this example firstly our array isn't nested
right nested arrays you have this one top level array which is having one two
three then a second array inside it in third array right now let's I write a
for loop here to show you guys better say console.log array.i and also let's
say I okay now if you see firstly the array looks like this at zero index one
and then one first index it is two then second index it is three third index it
is having an another array in nested level that fourth index it is having
another array now when I say flat is that converting removing this braces
removing this braces converting this arrays and merging into this existing
array like if you see here one two three then one two three then again removing
this array and merging this into the existing array got this so and the
number of nesting levels is actually defined by the parameter called depth if
you see it takes something value like like parameter which is depth here if
you see the maximum if you see the maximum recursion depth it says now
also if you see the definition it is actually pretty much like DSA it returns
a new array with all sub-array elements concatenated into it recursively up to
the specified depth now if someone says that you know a front-end developer
doesn't need a data section algorithm knowledge ask him to flatten the array
write polyfill for the flat now without your DSA knowledge do you understand
sub-array recursion call stack recursion right how would you do that so never
fall in that trap that hey DSA is not treated everywhere it revolves around
I've shown you reduce example using you know prefix some so every language does
it but they have library built it such as that friend and people don't use it
much extent but we need to know if you want to build the libraries like if you
want to be a really good at it okay now guys how would you approach this
question basic which algo will work here hey have you went to lead code
flatten
let's have you seen this question
right there are too many things these are directly asked in interval questions
okay I'm getting directly related to JS wait this is a question it is asked now
this is this is where you are trying to apply recursions and trying to go
through it but here in order to make it more useful what we have given we also
need a parameter called depth so one thing if you want to approach anything
right you might have you might have got you might write like what is the way
that you approach a DSA problem it's like simple right thinking them from a
brute force and how would you do it what algorithm should apply here right those
step-by-step things that you whatever you might have learned till now let's
apply those knowledge itself okay first let me write down the basic syntax array
dot prototype dot let's say I'm trying to build my flat then you have function
called my flat let's say this is a simple function doesn't need anything
name or anything but let's say this is what it is and it takes something called
as a depth here okay once it has stepped now okay some bits is travels and add it
into new array and return it cool but that's fine that we are returning it
let's say okay some with I'll do something like as you suggest let's say
const response I have array I'm returning this response okay and I'm
through this I said is dot length now what should I return it how should I
handle the conditions inside this some bit
array right you have to think how would you handle this firstly one simple okay
guys think if you can think hollows I'll solve it pretty basic pretty easy this
one only one condition you have to do it when to call okay think that firstly
when to call recursion what would be the condition when to call a recursion or
when we can directly add element into response array if you answer these two
things Arun says that when the index has length more than one okay right answer
right right I would agree with that point anyone else has anyone else the
other way around I don't can I take that if if you remember last class we have
discussed to check whether a particular item is item data drive is an array or
not we can do that thing also right if a particular index value is an array then
we can excuse it if not we can have to call a recursion on that do you remember
array dot is array page did you remember array dot is array condition okay yeah
that's that's a way we can go even Arun's point is also right but think of
it if you if you have done DP logic also dynamic programming that would be it a
basic recursion would solve it not needed DP where you try to memorize the
steps let's say if if I'll solve a basic condition if it's an array then we have
to do something else I have to directly add a response dot push of this now I
have to do something here I have to check another condition also here
the this can you think of it what would be the second condition I have to check
here firstly other than like yeah another loop here but how many loops you will be
keep on adding some bit if array is found or because it can be end time nested right
end time nested in the inside array inside another array inside another array yeah so
when you have depth level going when you have a chaining depth what could be the right way
how would you travel for you know like a tree when you have a node then you have its children
right you travel next or left dot or a right element root dot left or root dot right or
anything combination but before that before that guys do you see another condition that
only if I have to come inside this condition only if depth is greater than 0 if depth is
not greater than 0 I can push an array into it directly right only if depth is greater
than 0 that many for loops I should add inside it or else that many recursion calls I should
do it is that point clear firstly guys okay now what is the value of depth is doing now
when I say that you know depth one it will go and check that okay one two three fine
now I see that depth one I have to remove this I'll remove this one I'll merge here
I can see that this is depth level two I won't touch it this one I'll push it as it is again
this is depth one so I'll add it I'll remain it now this the reason this was left behind
was this was nested inside nested got this point somewhere this is talking about depth
only when depth is greater than 0 we should go or else we have to push it directly now
inside this let's say I don't think why you are not able to think it let's say I have
to push it again but I have to push it based on some condition whatever array I have whatever
array I have I'll say that this dot I again in order to call a recursion I'll say that
get my flat with depth of less than one you guys understand this point what just happened
I've reduced the depth so that again I'll call this function recursively I'll call it
again once that is resolved this will be pushed into it yeah guys give me thumbs up thumbs
down if you are able to understand this logic if not let me know how this is working but let
me show you this that it is actually supposed to work it I'll keep it on to the top
yeah just a second let's say I do flat to also I try to make it
first let's see this if this is working fine clearing it node flat dot JS okay firstly we
had an input just a second okay I need to call my flat
yeah this is working fine now also I'll try to output firstly console dot console dot log
array let's verify this one okay yeah cool so let me go to iPad I think this should be
basics to you guys once you have completed DSA have you cleared mocks guys right now
let's say what is the input we have took
now when this is happening this brace is depth level 0 this level is depth level 1
this braces depth level 2 firstly is this point clear what is meant by depth okay once now when
let's say if my depth value is 0 what they are saying is that directly you need not to
flatten anything there they are they are telling how many levels I should flatten okay if depth
level is 0 they I can return directly whatever array they have given to me isn't it I need not
to flatten anything only when they say that a flatten till depth level 1 then I should go
1 2 3 then 1 then 2 comma 3 then 4 5 6 this is for 1 when they say 2 I can go further
okay this is what I can do nice is this clear is this point clear now what was happening in
the code what was happening in the code was if you remember whenever we are actually you
know coming across this part whenever we are coming across this part we are checking whether
the value provider depth is greater than 0 if the greater than 0 is there then we were actually
taking this array whole array taking this whole array and we are calling this function again let's
say this array 1 2 dot 3 dot my flat reducing depth let's say we passed you we are reducing
depth by 1 now on this level when this again actually goes by it if it flattens again this
becomes again this one isn't it so this is what is happening we did a multiple recursion calls
for this one like for this one we did it two times for this one we did it one time we called
it three times if I can dry run and show it to you like in the debugging mode what's actually
let me open a debugger tool
yes let's say this what's happening firstly this keyword is having five elements with a
zeroth index pointing at the first zeroth index so this is not an array type so this
condition is failing it came here and we were pushing that element now then we went on to
second element then we went on to third element okay now if you see in the local my flat in the
response array we have stored 0 1 2 which is 1 2 3 items now when we go to the third index index
number 3 let's see where the call comes here okay what is it firstly it is executing this
part so let me comment this one I don't need this both things let me let us execute firstly
directly this one okay I'll move forward for two levels now if you see what just happened when
I is equal to three the whatever we have stored it is of data type of an array and the current
depth if you see depth we are talking about is 2 now what just happened here let's see this
okay when we are saying that we are calling back again my flat with increasing it now and if I try
to do this let's say if I try to triple lot and of do this this of I okay clear this of I I'm
getting this an array which I'm spreading it here whole array I'm spreading it and I'm calling on
my depth because why I'm spreading it here is that actually cleaning up one level of depth I'm just
trying to remove this like first array like whenever I do let's say there's an array let's
I store it in the memory called array one I say one two three and let's say I console log
spreading an array one you see I've removed that array symbol so that's why I've spread it first
level and then I called my function with reduced depth is this point here guys why I am calling
back again because my depth is still in still to right once I call this now what just happened
if you see here we went on to push here firstly now the current array looks like this it has
at the 0th index it has one if you remember at 0th index it has one and the first index just 2 and
3 and even in the response array there is nothing else as of now if we keep on adding it if you see
there are two things present it's now if you see once we have iterated over this part once we have
completed iteration over this part now what it is stored is 1 2 3 and 1 2 3 because two levels of
depth recursion calls are completed now then it is going again for this part 2 3 4 ok because I
is pointing at 4 here I go back again now if I see that depth level is still 1 it will push it
it will push all the elements and then we'll be able to see the output as I hope I hope this
example is clear how that array dot flat is working is this anyone who still don't understand
this to let me know and if this part is clear I think this is it when it comes here when you
come for higher order functions writing you know polyfills nothing much more than for
considering higher order functions will be asked okay next class we'll discuss again call bind
apply and few more things few more important questions let me commit this
I actually picked it up flat as extra it was not part of thing that I have to
do but I thought to discuss this because this is something interesting and if someone asks you
this one you should be able to do it guys again rechecking before I start the doubt
session is this things clear to you all like what we have discussed in today's class all of the
topics cool so I'll start doubt session guys then I received very less the amount of thumbs up just
want to check like again started out session guys but do let me know I can recall few names
I have to some bits in class Pramod Rajni Hemanki guys are you able to follow up did you guys
understand upendra right in that case guys keep practicing this one if someone asks you polyfills
I hope you will be able to explain them using a flat is really simple easy you should be able
to also build that one someone asked it just want to know when I asked a flat no one told
me that I would be applying a recursion when do you guys think that recursion should be applied
yeah Rajni will do that give me a minute I'll open whatsapp and share the link yes when do
you think that recursion should be applied any idea guys when would you go for recursion
solving sub problems are solving same sort of problems same problems right when you have
same sort of problems again and again occurring so you don't write a logics for them so in order
to call you create a one function you will keep calling that function and amount of time so
you have that same sort of problems right okay whatsapp web and how would you figure out like
when DPA should be applied I'm just thinking like you know asking you some random stuff
when how do you come to know that when if there are like you know DPA should be applied
right so whenever you come across a point where you see that there are same sub problems like
whenever you are in recursion if you see that there are some same parameters are being passed
each time and same time you are getting the same result in that use cases you actually use DPA
where you try to optimize that hey once if I solve the problem why should I do it again
let's let's let's you know optimize that logic guys be okay I've shared whatsapp chat actually
nice there's any any other doubts in our class today's class or anything else if you have
anything please feel free to ask I'm here for some time or else we can close the session if
there are no doubts I'll wait for one two minutes how's your appraisers going on this
month have you got your appraisers write your current form guys no not yet
okay report to release next week seems to be okay hey why where do you work upendra
which form is it is it happening with everyone or like bank based out of Bangalore Bangalore
there's a few people in Jigini and work from and my related works there I've been to Jigini
start of my career I started with HCL so guys I don't see any doubts coming up so can we close
the session tonight I hope you get back the one hour that you have and try to solve the
assignments guys try to keep preparing yourself for the context upcoming context next week
revise those topics in case you have anything bring me in what's app or in the class we'll
pick it up and we'll try to discuss that thought topic okay so from my side that's it guys then
see you in the next class where we pick up few more polyfills and try to revise few more concepts
like as we did we revise the concept then we went on to build a polyfill happy shivarathri
all happy happy shivarathri upendra thank you all guys for attending hope to see you soon on the
Saturday yeah it takes time for the practice I completely agree some bit with with time you
will get it so whenever I'm explaining I just want to be sure that the topics whatever I'm
trying to explain you you are able to understand that part and with repeating with you do it
personally when you type it down you'll get it further it's like when I'm typing it down it's
like a magic for you guys firstly so until you try to repeat it you won't be able to feel it up
okay it's like virat koly playing cover drive right until this you don't practice it you won't
get it we know that okay what is cover drive when the ball is pitching up on the fifth
side some you guys try to you know play it we know it but it comes with a practice same thing
so otherwise then with that I'll close the session for today see you on Saturday thank
you Muneeshwara bye bye guys good night take care again happy shivarathri all